たいしたもんじゃないですか｡
ｷﾐが そう？
それも屍から
はぎとったんですか？
(松陽)屍を喰らう
鬼が出ると聞いて来てみれば➡
そうして自分の身を
護ってきたんですか｡
(松陽)童一人で
屍の身ぐるみをはき➡
また ずいぶんと
かわいい鬼がいたものですね｡
♪♪～
だけど そんな剣
もういりませんよ｡
人に怯え 自分を護るためだけに
ふるう剣なんて➡
もう捨てちゃいなさい｡
くれてあげますよ｡ 私の剣｡
I came after hearing about
a corpse-eating demon...
そいつの
本当の使い方を知りたきゃ➡
ついてくるといい｡
Would that be you?
A rather cute demon.
Did you also take that from a corpse?
A single child stripping corpses
to protect himself, is it?
That's very impressive.
However, you no longer need that sword.
A sword that's only swung in self-defense,
while fearing others,
should be thrown away.
I shall give you my sword.
If you wish to learn how
to properly use it...
Then come with me.
(銀時)
おい… その手で触れんじゃねえ｡
Hey...
Get your hands off her.
この女に触れんじゃねえ｡
Get your stinkin' hands off this woman.
(地雷亜)お… お前は！
Y-You're...?!
(月詠)銀時…｡
Gintoki...
Why did you...
ぬし なぜ
こんなところに来た…｡
come here...?
["The More Precious the Burden, the Heavier
and More Difficult It Is to Shoulder It."]
そんな体で…
逃げろと言ったのに｡
Look at yourself...
I told you to run...
ﾊﾞｶ者め…｡
You fool...
死にゃあしねえよ ｵﾚは｡
I won't be dying.
死にゃあしねえよ… 誰も｡
Nobody will be dying.
もう この吉原で誰も死なせねえ｡
I won't let anyone die in Yoshiwara.
ｵﾚたちはな
お前を一人にはしねえよ｡
You see...
We aren't gonna leave you all alone.
ﾌﾌﾌﾌｯ… ｵﾚが張った糸をたどり
ここを嗅ぎつけたか｡
You followed my threads
to find this place?
奇特なことだ｡
Commendable.
蜘蛛の糸を極楽目指して
登るどころか➡
They say one climbs the spider
thread to reach for paradise...
[Note: A reference to Ryunosuke Akutagawa's
"The Spider's Thread"]
地獄目指して
這いあがってくるとは…｡
Instead, you climb up to reach for hell.
お前さんのﾊﾞｶさ加減には➡
Your idiocy would leave Buddha
and Enma both speechless.
釈迦も閻魔もあきれようて｡
待て 銀時！
Wait, Gintoki...!
Don't bother telling me to run again.
逃げろなんて もう言わせねえよ｡
一人でなにもかも
背負い込もうなんざ➡
Trying to shoulder the burden
all by yourself?
みずくせえじゃねえか｡
Don't be such a stranger.
涙垂れ流して 助けを乞いやがれ｡
Weep and ask for help.
鼻水垂れ流してｵﾚにすがりやがれ｡
Lean on me with your runny nose.
泣きてえときには泣けばいいんだ｡
Cry when you feel like crying.
笑いたいときには笑えばいいんだ｡
Laugh when you feel like laughing.
ﾃﾒｴが醜いﾂﾗで
泣きわめいているときは➡
When you're tearing up with an ugly face,
それ以上 汚ねえﾂﾗで泣いてやる｡
I'll give you a good cry
with an uglier face.
ﾃﾒｴが腹抱えて笑ってるときは➡
When you're laughing so
hard your stomach hurts,
それ以上 ﾊﾞｶﾃﾞｶｲ声で笑ってやる｡
I'll laugh in a louder voice.
それでいいんだよ｡
That's how it should be.
ﾃﾒｴを捨てて 潔くきれいに
死んでいくなんてことより➡
It's far better to get dirty while
living true to yourself,
小汚くても ﾃﾒｴらしく
生きていくことのほうが➡
than to throw away yourself
and die a clean death.
よっぽど上等だ｡
お前が 荷を負うと？
You offer to carry her burden?
月詠の荷を お前も共に担うと？
You will help carry Tsukuyo's burden?
ﾌﾌﾌﾌｯ わからんのか｡
Don't you understand?
月詠にとっての荷は
お前以外の何ものでもない｡
You are Tsukuyo's burden.
お前たちがいなければ 月詠は
こんなに苦しむことはなかった｡
You people are the reason Tsukuyo
has suffered so much.
こんなに醜くなることはなかった｡
The reason she's grown so hideous.
月詠 腹が空いただろ｡
Tsukuyo, you must be hungry.
今 特上のｴｻを用意してやる｡
I shall prepare you a top class meal.
月を追い 巣に迷い込んだ
この哀れな虫ｹﾗをな｡
Of the pathetic worm who followed
the moon into my web.
I don't give a damn about
who you've betrayed.
ﾃﾒｴが どこで誰を
裏切ろうが かまやしねえ｡
将軍だろうが
どこぞの主君だろうが➡
Do whatever you like to the
Shogun or any other lords.
どうぞ好きにやりゃいい｡
だが ひとたび
師と名のっておきながら➡
But you called yourself her master
ﾃﾒｴ 弟子裏切ったな｡
and then you betrayed your student...
ｶﾞｷん頃から ﾃﾒｴを信じてたｺｲﾂを｡
who's believed in you
since she was a kid...
ずっと ﾃﾒｴを追いかけてたｺｲﾂを｡
Who's followed in your
footsteps for so long...
ﾃﾒｴは 食いもんにしたな｡
You made her your prey.
そんなもん 師とは呼ばねえ｡
You don't deserve to call
yourself her master...
そんなもん 師弟とは呼ばねえ！
You don't deserve to
call her your student.
消えろ｡
Get lost.
ｺｲﾂの前から
さっさと消えろってんだ｡
Don't ever show your face around
her again, you sick son of a bitch!!
腐れ外道！
This man...
《この男 獲物の目ではない｡
His eyes aren't that of a prey.
まして ｴｻの目でもない｡
Nor the eyes of a meal.
糸が震える》
My threads are quivering.
《かつて かかったことのない
得体の知れぬものの侵入に➡
My web is reacting to an
unprecedented invasion.
ｵﾚの巣が反応している｡
あれは あの目は…》
That's...
Those eyes are...!
地雷亜 巣にかかったのは
ﾃﾒｴのほうだ｡
Jiraia...
You're the one who's been
caught in a web.
ｵﾚの巣
土足で踏み荒らしたからには➡
My web.
Now that you've made
a mess of my place,
生きて出られると思うな｡
don't expect to leave alive.
うす汚ねえ体液ぶちまいて
くたばりやがれ｡
Spill your rotten gut as you die!
ﾌｯ！ 食い合いか…｡
A battle between hunters?
Amusing.
おもしろい｡
どちらが 巣の主か
その身をもって 知るがいい！
I'll show you who the
master of this web is.
糸の張るところ
たとえ 六道なりとも➡
Any place with my threads, be it the
six realms, shall be part of my web!
我が巣と成り果てる｡
♪♪～
その手負いの身で
ｵﾚを捉えられるか？
You cannot catch me with those injuries.
外に逃げるつもりか｡ 甘いわ！
Do you intend to escape outside?!
Fool!
甘ぇのは ﾃﾒｴだ｡
You're the fool.
Gotcha.
つ～かま～えた｡
さぁ 晩餐会の時間だ｡
たらふく食わせてもらうぜ！
Now, time for supper.
Let's dig in!
If you wish to learn how
to properly use it...
((ｿｲﾂの本当の使い方を知りたきゃ
ついてくるといい｡
Then come with me.
これからは ｿｲﾂを振るい…｡
From now on, you will swing that sword.
Not to cut down your enemies.
敵を斬るためではない｡
弱き己を斬るために｡
Not to cut away your weaknesses
and protect yourself.
己を護るのではない｡
己の魂を護るために))
But to protect your very soul.
てや～っ!!
うぉ～っ！
でや～っ！
銀時！
Gintoki!
なぜ…｡
How...?
お前が ｵﾚと拮抗する力を…｡
How can you have power that rivals mine?
By someone unable to abandon
their sense of self...
己を捨てることもできん連中に…｡
己の居場所欲しさに
仲間も斬れん連中に…｡
By someone who can't even sever their ties,
just to have a place to return to...?!
ｵﾚは すべてを捨ててきた｡
I have sacrificed everything...
My sense of self, my home,
even my comrades...
己の存在も 居場所も 仲間も…｡
獲物のために… お前のために！
All for my prey...
For you...
なのに なぜ… なぜなんだ!?
Yet why...? Why?!
You still can't understand?
まだ わからねえのか｡
ｵﾒｴが捨てたもんのなかには
大切な荷も まざってたんだよ｡
Some of the things you sacrificed
were too important.
仲間を捨てた？ 違う｡
仲間を失うのが怖かったんだろう｡
You abandoned your comrades?
No.
You were afraid of losing your comrades.
You fought alone?
一人で戦ってきた？ 違う！
No!
最初から 一人であれば➡
You wouldn't have to feel the pain of solitude
if you'd been alone to begin with.
孤独になる苦しみも
ねえからだろう｡
You abandoned your sense of self?
己を捨てた？ 違う！
No.
ﾃﾒｴは 背負う苦しみも
背負われる苦しみからも逃げた➡
You were running away from the pain
you caused and the pain you endured.
ただの臆病者だ！
You're just a coward!
ｺｲﾂは もう
ﾃﾒｴなんかより よっぽど強いよ｡
She's far stronger than
you could ever be.
臆病者の相手は 臆病者で十分だ｡
A coward is enough to deal
with another coward.
ﾃﾒｴの相手は このｵﾚで十分だ｡
I'm enough to take you.
ぬかせ！
Silence!
ﾃﾒｴに師匠の名を語る資格はねえ｡
You don't have the right to
call yourself her master!
ﾃﾒｴに荷ごと弟子を背負う
背中があるかぁ！
You don't have the strength to shoulder
a student and their pain!!
Gintoki...
銀時…｡
帰るぞ お前の居場所に｡
Let's go back.
To your home...
(月詠)地雷亜 やめろ！
Jiraia! Stop!
もうやめとけ｡
Give up already.
ﾃﾒｴの巣には 何もいやしねえよ｡
There's nothing in your web.
そこにいんのは 最初から➡
This whole time, there was only
ever a pathetic little spider,
はるか頭上の
月の光をあおぎ見て➡
spinning threads into the sky while
gazing at the distant moon.
空に向かって糸を吐き続ける
哀れな蜘蛛だけだ｡
ﾌｯ… 何を世迷い言を｡
What are you babbling about?
そんなことは
とうの昔に知ってるさ｡
I already knew that long ago.
Stop! Jiraia!
やめろ 地雷亜！
いい それで… それでいい｡
Yes...
This is how...
How it should be...
蜘蛛が地に消えゆくか…｡
The spider will disappear
in a pool of blood.
存外… 期待していたほどの
感慨はないな｡
It doesn't...
feel as good as I expected...
己を殺すなどということは｡
to be killed by myself.
((ｵﾚは ｵﾚを殺したいんだ))
I want to kill myself.
地雷亜… ぬし｡
Jiraia, were you...?
Jiraia, your final prey...
(全蔵)地雷亜
お前の最後の獲物は…｡
お前自身だったってわけかい｡
was you yourself, huh?
お前の狙いは 手塩にかけて
鍛え上げた己の分身を➡
Your goal wasn't to kill the clone
you'd raised and trained.
殺すことなんかじゃねえ｡
最愛の弟子… 己自身に
殺されることだったんだろ｡
It was to be killed by your beloved
student, as yourself.
か… 頭の息子か？
Th-The boss's son, is it...?
一度会うたな｡
We met once before.
親父殿と仲間の仇
再び とりに来たか｡
Have you come to avenge your
father and comrades again?
仇なんざ とうの昔に
とる気は失せたぜ｡
I lost interest in revenge a long time ago.
地に落ち もがく蜘蛛なんざ➡
I have no interest in crushing a spider
who's fallen to earth.
潰す気にもなりゃしねえよ 段臓｡
...Danzo.
すべて 調査済みというわけか｡
So you've done your research.
蜘蛛手の地雷亜… 本名 鳶田段臓｡
Jiraia the Spider.
Real name: Danzo Tobita.
伊賀の郷氏の元に生まれ
幼少の頃より 忍術を納め➡
Born to a country samurai in Iga and mastered
ninja techniques at a young age.
その才は
神童と呼ばれるほどのものだった｡
Your natural aptitude had people
calling you a prodigy.
伊賀は 郷氏どもが 年中
覇権争いを繰り広げている土地だ｡
The samurai in Iga were
fighting year round.
鳶田家は 伊賀でも有数の大家｡
The Tobita family was one
of the larger families in Iga.
そのうえ 嫡男が
すこぶる腕が立つとなりゃ➡
With such a talented son in line to take over,
its foes weren't going to stand by idly.
ﾔﾂらも黙っちゃいねえ｡
生き残ったのは
お前と 年端もいかない妹｡
The only survivors were you
and your still young sister.
お前は 一族郎党を
皆殺しにされていながら➡
You felt ashamed of the skills which kept
you alive while everyone else was killed.
その類稀なる腕ゆえ 生き恥を
さらさせられることとなった｡
With the life of your only remaining
family hostage,
ただ一人の肉親の命を質に｡
you were forced to swear fealty to your hated
enemy, what would have been your prey.
憎むべき敵に… 喰らうべき獲物に
忠誠を誓ったんだ｡
お前の歪んだ忠誠心が
生まれたのは その頃だろう｡
That gave birth to your twisted
sense of devotion.
滅私奉公… 文字どおり
自分の身を捨てて➡
Sacrifice oneself for the country.
You literally sacrificed your sense
of self to devote yourself to work.
仇のために働いた｡
いや
捨てるしかなかったんだろう｡
No, you had no choice.
一族を根絶やした仇に仕える
その憎しみ 悲しみ｡
Your only escape from the hate,
sorrow, and shame of serving the ones
who exterminated your family
恥辱の念から逃れるには
己という存在を忘れきり➡
was to forget your identity and focus on mechanically
carrying out mission after mission.
ただ 目の前の任務を
機械的にこなしていくしかない｡
お前は そんな自分に
陶酔することで➡
You used that intoxication
to escape the pain.
苦しみから逃れようとした｡
だが そんな兄の姿を
見ていられなくなったのだろう｡
However, your sister couldn't bear
seeing her older brother like that.
((もういい… もういいの｡
No more... No more.
私のために
ﾑﾘするのは もうやめて｡
Stop pushing yourself for my sake.
兄者… 自分の人生を生きて｡
Dear brother, live your own life.
自由に… 自分のために生きて))
Live freely for yourself.
Your sister took her own life.
(全蔵)お前の妹は
自ら 命を絶った｡
どれだけ獲物を喰らっても
どれだけ己を痛めつけても➡
After all the prey you took,
all the pain to your body,
you still couldn't protect your sister.
妹を護れなかった｡ その痛みは
いつまでも お前を苦しめた｡
To this very day, you're still
haunted by that fact.
そうして お前は
最も 自分が忌むべき方法で➡
And so you attempted to kill yourself
in the worst possible way.
お前自身を殺そうとした｡
You would become the enemy of
the beloved student you'd raised,
己が手塩にかけて育てた
最愛の弟子の仇として➡
その手にかかって 死ぬ｡
and die by her hands.
それが 妹を護れなかったお前が
自身に科した罰…｡
That was your self-inflicted punishment
for failing to protect your sister.
違うな｡
No...
I was just scared.
ただ 怖かっただけさ…｡
お前さんの言うとおり
ｵﾚは また失うのが怖くて➡
Just as you said,
I was scared of losing anything else...
荷を負うことをやめた
ただの臆病者｡
A coward who was too scared
to bear the burden.
ゆえに惹かれたんだ｡
That is why I became drawn to her.
((わっちは
吉原と日輪を護りたいんじゃ！))
I wanna protect Yoshiwara and Hinowa!
(地雷亜)小さき背中で 荷を
一身に背負おうとする その童に｡
The child who tried to shoulder
everything on that small back...
ゆえに 己のすべてを
伝授しようとしたんだ｡
That was why I taught
you everything I knew.
傷つけたくなかった…
ｵﾚのように｡
I didn't want you to be hurt...
The way I was...
失う苦しみを味わうくらいなら➡
If we are doomed to experience
the suffering from a loss,
最初から何も背負わなければいい｡
then why shoulder the
burden to begin with?
居場所も仲間もいらない…｡
No need for a home or comrades...
だが ｵﾚの思いとは裏腹に➡
But you defied my expectations...
お前の周りには いつの間にか
仲間が… 居場所ができていた｡
You've managed to find
friends... a home...
お前は ｵﾚにはない
強さを持っていた｡
You possessed a strength I never did.
背負う苦しみからも➡
The strength to not run away from the pain
you caused, the pain you endured...
背負われる苦しみからも
逃げぬ強さ｡
怖かったのさ… また失うのが｡
I was scared of losing
someone else again...
お前が ｵﾚのもとから
遠く離れていくようで｡
You were headed somewhere
far away from me...
ｵﾚは その手を引き戻そうと➡
I...
...was trying to draw you back...
お前を
ｵﾚと同じ目にあわせていた｡
To the same fate I suffered...
ｵﾚは 結局 お前も妹も…
何も護ってなどいなかった｡
In the end, I wasn't protecting
you or my sister...
ｵﾚが護っていたのは 自分だけだ｡
I was only protecting myself...
そんな自分に愛想が尽きた｡
And I became tired of myself.
ただ それだけのことさ｡
That was all...
ﾌﾌ… もう何も
背負うまいと思ったのに➡
I planned on never shouldering
another burden,
いつの間にか
また荷を背負い込んでいる｡
yet I'd managed to do it again.
もう 誰にも
背負わせまいと思ったのに➡
I planned on never forcing anyone
else to shoulder my burden,
いつの間にか
また何かを背負わせている｡
yet I'd managed to do it again.
月詠…
つまらぬものを背負わせたな…｡
Tsukuyo, I forced you to shoulder
a worthless burden.
すまなかった…｡
I am sorry...
もっと 早くに
話をしてほしかった｡
I wish you had told me this sooner.
わっちにも 遠慮なく
その荷 分けてほしかった｡
I wish you had allowed me
to share your burden.
そうしたら きっと
また違った答えが出せていたはず｡
We would have been able to
arrive at a different answer.
弟子を荷ごと背負うのが
師匠の役目なら➡
If the master's duty is to shoulder
the student along with their pain,
弟子の役目は なんじゃ｡
what is the student's duty?
師を背負えるまでに
大きくなることじゃ｡
To grow strong enough
to shoulder the master.
軽い… 軽いのう 師匠｡
You're light...
So light, Master...
ぬしは こんなにも
軽かったんじゃな｡
I never knew you were so light...
見えるか？ 師匠｡
Can you see, Master?
ああ… ああ｡ 見える｡
Yes...
Yes...!
I can see...
今まで見たことがないほどの➡
A moon more beautiful...
than any...I've ever seen...
きれいな月だ…｡
大した弟子だな｡
That's one helluva student.
師匠を背負えるまで
大きくなるのが 弟子の務めか｡
A student's duty is to grow strong enough
to shoulder the master, huh?
ｵﾚは 親父には背負われてばかりで
そんなﾏﾈしてやれなんだな｡
I was always relying on my old man,
so I was never able to do that.
ｵﾚもだ｡
...Same here.
[Preview]
Tsukuyo-chan!
Let's go out and play!
Hey, wake up, damn it.
We're hitting the pachinko parlor.
You probably got a bunch
saved up, right?
["Watch Out For A Set of Women and A Drink"]
I'll blow it all for you.
[Ohh! JUMP-san!! Don't use profanity
in the important parts!]
[See you next time.]
♬『ゼッコーチョー！』
♬～